Guide to the T. S. Eliot Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
T. S. Eliot collection
1920-1972
YCAL MSS 523
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.8
(2 boxes)
Contains letters from T. S. Eliot to various individuals, drafts of writings by Eliot, and writings on Eliot by Helen Gardner. Portions of the collection are photocopies and photostats of material held by other repositories.
Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from various sources. Provenance is listed at folder level when known.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
This collection includes photocopies of material held by other repositories. Photocopies and the location of the originals are noted in the finding aid.
T. S. Eliot (1888-1965)
T. S. (Thomas Stearns) Eliot, was a poet, playwright, and literary critic. He was born in the United States and moved to the United Kingdom in 1914 and was naturalized as a British subject in 1927.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains letters from T. S. Eliot to various individuals, drafts of writings by Eliot, and writings on Eliot by Helen Gardner. Portions of the collection are photocopies and photostats of material held by other repositories.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1930-1957. II. Writings, 1934-1972.
Authors -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Poets -- 20th Century; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965; Gardner, Helen, 1908-1986
- Correspondence, 1930-1957; Series I; 8
  - DeVane, William., 1948 October 11 (Box 1)
    Custodial History
    Gift of William DeVane, 1948
  - Haight, Gordon Sherman, 1952 January 2 (Box 1)
    Gift of Gordon Sherman Haight, 1971
  - Heggem, Mrs. Melvin, 1952 December 30 (Box 1)
    Related Archival Materials note
    Original letter is at Mabel Zoe Wilson Library, Western Washington State College
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopy of the original
  - Pope, John C., 1946 -1947 (Box 1)
    Gift of John Pope, 1980
    Includes letter from Pope to Donald Gallup concerning the letters
  - Porteus, Hugh Gordon, 1933-1957; 2 (Box 1)
    Purchased on the S. W. Childs Fund, 1970
    Includes original letters and photocopies
  - Wells, James, 1930 June 24 (Box 1)
    Gift of Walter F. Pforzheimer, 1940
  - Zukofsky, Louis, 1930 June 20, November 6 (Box 1)
    Gift of Norman Holmes Pearson, 1956
- Writings, 1920-1972, undated; Series II; 9
  - "Brief Treatise on the Criticism of Poetry." Typescript corrected and signed, 1920 March (Box 1)
    Purchased on the Adele Gutman Nathan Theatrical Collection Fund from Serendipity Books, 2011
    Accompanied by "Three Critical Essays on Modern English Poetry" by T.S. Eliot, Aldous Huxley, and F. S. Flint, printed version. Includes Eliot's "Brief Treatise on the Criticism of Poetry"
  - "Confidential Clerk." Typescript mimeograph, annotated, with sketches by Hutchinson Scott, undated (Box 1)
    Purchased Ezra Pound Archive Fund from Black Sun Books, 1989
    Scenic designers copy with notes for first production
  - "The Family Reunion: Act I, Scenes 1 & 2." Typescript, undated (Box 1)
    Gift of Howard & Phyllis Mott, 1967
    Includes prompt copy for production, April 1957, by Dorothy Black. Notebook, interleaved, with manuscript annotations
  - "Murder in the Cathedral." Autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1)
    Original manuscript is at the Houghton Library, Harvard University
    Purchased, 1937
    Photostat of the original. Includes excerpts of letter from Henry W. Eliot, Jr. to Kr. Keogh, 1937 May 29, regarding the manuscript
  - "Rannoch, by Glencoe." Autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1)
    Photostat of the original
  - "The Rock: Chorus X (Final Chorus)." Autograph manuscript, 1934 March 19; 2 (Box 1)
    Purchased, 1969
    Includes original and photocopy and letter from Eliot to Mrs. L. M. Cage, 1934 April 27
  - Writings by Helen Gardner on Eliot, 1941-1972 (Box 2)
    Photocopies of originals. Includes Gardner's bibliography of writings on Eliot and writings on Eliot by Gardner